## Konstantin Burlachenko Ph.D. candidacy in Computer Science program, CEMSE division at KAUST



@ burlachenkok@gmail.com @ konstantin.burlachenko@kaust.edu.sa 

in linkedin.com/in/burlachenkok github.com/burlachenkok



i Homepage: https://burlachenkok.github.io

I have co-created state-of-the-art systems for Machine Learning, Graphics, Vision, and Computational Physics, exploiting hardware via DSL and using contemporary areas of Math and CS. My current focus is Federated Learning, a subfield of Machine Learning co-invented by my advisor in 2016. It has become a key part of the "US National Artificial Intelligence Research and Development Plan" in May 2023. My dissertation title is "Optimization Methods and Software for Federated Learning".

## EDUCATION

2020-Now	KSA: Ph.D. program in CEMSE/CS Program at KAUST. Member of Prof. Peter Richtárik's Optimization and
	Machine Learning Lab in KAUST AI initiative led by Jürgen Schmidhuber. Transcript: Link-1. GPA: 3.81/4.0.
2015-2019	USA, Stanford : Graduate Non-Degree Program. <i>Transcript</i> : Link-2. <i>GPA</i> : 3.96/4.3
2015-2018	USA, Stanford : Data, Models and Optimization Graduate Certificate Link-3 (Program)
2016 - 2019	USA, Stanford : Artificial Intelligence Graduate Certificate Link-4 (Program)
2003-2009	Russia, Bauman Moscow State Technical University: Master Degree (Bologn process equivalent) in Com-
	puter Science and Control Systems. GPA: Not Applicable. (Original scans)
Conferences and	ACM CoNEXT 2023; Rising Stars in Al Symposium 2023 and 2024, EMNLP-2022; ICML-2022; ICML-2021;
Summer Schools	NeurlPS-2021; ACM CoNEXT 2021; ACM SIGGRAPH 2012; Regularization Methods for ML 2021; The PRAI-
	RIE/MIAI AI 2021; Oxford ML-2021; The HSE/MIPT Optimization without Border.

## EXPERIENCE

### August 2021

### Research Scientist Intern (AI), FACEBOOK INC., USA, Menlo Park

After passing competitive interviews I have read several papers that Dr. Hao-Jun Michael Shi has recommended. We had several discussions and we've selected the research topic that is important to the company and at the same time for my Ph.D. The internship has not happened due to the absence of a J1 VISA. Distributed Math Optimization | Al | Federated Learning

### Now September 2020

## CS Ph.D. candidacy and a member of Prof. Peter Richtárik OPTIMIZATION AND ML LAB<sup>2</sup>, KAUST, KSA

- Narrow area of my research: Federated Learning(FL), Stochastic Distributed Math Optimization for Al.
- ▶ Broad areas of my interests: Math Optimization, AI/ML, Compute Optimization, Software Systems, GPGPU, Computer Vision, Computer Graphics, Networks, Cryptography, Control, Physical Simulation.
- ▶ During Sep 2022 Sep 2023 I was a Member of Center of Excellence in Data Science and Artificial Intelligence SDAIA-KAUST AI (invitation letter). During my affilation I have co-initiated a joint project.
- Awards: (1) Dean's Award 2020, KAUST; (2) Grant from SDAIA 2022; (3) Dean's List Award 2023, KAUST; (4) AMD Radeon Instinct MI50 from AMD Inc.

Distributed Math Optimization | Federated Learning | Applied Math | Computer Vision | Sytems | Cryptography | C/C++ CUDA AVX512 Python CMake Qt/PyQt PyTorch TF Latex Git Google Tests Bash

### August 2020 March 2019

## Principal Engineer Level 18 | Foundation AI Lab, HUAWEI, Moscow

- ▶ R&D in internal ML Systems middleware for HUAWEI HiSilicon and manage team of 6 members.
- ▶ Present HiSilicon solutions for engineers, scientists working with ML/AI. OpenTalks.AI, HUAWEI News.
- ▶ R&D in internal projects in Machine Learning/Systems HUAWEI Consumer Business Group.
- ▶ Awards: Grade "A" for a 2019-2020 Year Progress with a one-time payment bonus.

Math Optimization | Al | Custome ISA | C/C++ | Python | TVM | Java | Google Protobuf | CMake | Qt | TF | SQL

### March 2019 July 2014

### Senior Developer Technology Engineer Level IC3, NVIDIA, Moscow

- ▶ Driveworks SDK SDK for self-driving cars adopted by automotive partners. Computer vision, machine learning, calibration, egomotion. Implementation and presentation of the modules internally.
- PhysX/Apex SDK An industry standard for game physics simulation, graphical special effects. Internal implementation and communication with extra customers (Blizzard).
- cuDNN/cuBLAS libraries GPU computation libraries used by more than 1M customers in machine learning and HPC. Implementation, Documentation, and collaboration with Mathworks.
- ► RAPIDS GPU based implementation of SkLearn, XgBoost, Pandas. I was resnposible for SkLearn.

CUDA | GLSL | C++ | AARCH64 | SSE2/ARM NEON | Linux | Windows | PS4 | XBox | OpenGL | Google Tests | GitLab Perl | Python | CMake | Make | Qt | Git | TensorFlow | Computer Vision | Graphics | Deep Learning | CppCheck |

<sup>1.</sup> Federated Learning: Strategies for Improving Communication Efficiency [J.Konečný, H.B.McMahan, F.X.Yu, P.Richtarik, A.T.Suresh, D.Bacon, NIPS 2016]

<sup>2.</sup> To avoid academic disputes over authorship order and focus on work, the Lab mostly adopts the concept of "Every Author as First Author" arXiv:2304.01393

### July 2014

### Senior Developer Engineer | Yandex Video Team, YANDEX, Moscow

- May 2013
- ► Text and statistical machine learning features for Yandex Video Search.
- ▶ Infrastructure for storage and analysis of all web documents with embedded video on the WWW
- ► Infrastructure to show plots for internal team's processes
- Awards: Two one-time payment bonuses due to the delivery of products in production.

C++ Google Protobuf JavaScript Bash Python Computer Science HTML/JS/CSS SVN MapReduce ML

### April 2013 March 2012

### Team Lead Physics Engine Developer, FITTING REALITY, Moscow

- ▶ Develop library for clothing simulation in CUDA and in OpenCL with facade interface to C++/C#.
- ► Custom render engine for clothing visualization compatible with OpenGL 1.2.
- ▶ Prepare elements of the demo to investors. Carry internal MATH/CS/PHYS trainings.
- ▶ Manage team of 4 members. **Awards**: Funding visit of SIGGRAPH 2012, USA conference.

C++ C OpenGL GLSL Qt Posix WinAPI QMake CUDA OpenCL Physics Graphics Ogre C#

### March 2012 September 2010

### Software Developer Engineer, ACRONIS, Moscow

- ► Key member of GUI team for Acronis Backup and Recovery 2011 Enterprise
- ▶ Profiling and optimization of the codebase working in user/kernel space for Windows OS.

C++ C WinAPI WinDbg VmWare Specialized GUI library SVN SysInternals CppCheck ASM x86 AqTime

### September 2010 March 2009

### Senior Software Developer Engineer, CAPITAL RESEARCH, Moscow

Developed Firefox plugin to create the three-dimensional HTML view for basics HTML elements.

Firefox C++ WinAPI HTML/JS/CSS Windows OpenGL GLSL SVN

### June 2009 December 2006

### C++ Programming Engineer, FLINT AND CO, Moscow

- ► Created several computer games with computer vision and graphics part, hardware drivers.
- ► Spent time on factory floors to test and analyze the quality of my solutions. Carry trips to customers.

  C++ SDL Posix WinApi Development Image Library Low level programming Computer Vision OpenGL SVN

### November 2006 March 2006

### C++ Programming Engineer (Part time work), ASTRASOFT TECHNOLOGY, Moscow

▶ Developed visual elements of management system based on Qt and OpenGL.

C++ Qt Windows OpenGL SVN

## \* Presentations

### FEB-2024 Rising Stars in Al Symposium KAUST, KSA:

Unlocking FedNL: Self-Contained Compute-Optimized Implementation 🗗 link

DEC-2023 ACM DistributedML2023, France: Federated Learning is Better with Non-Homomorphic Encryption.

JUNE-2023 SIAM: Conference on Optimization (OP23), USA:

Fl\_PyTorch : Optimization Research Simulator for Federated Learning 🗹 link

MARCH-2023 VCC OPEN HOUSE 2023 event, KSA: FedNL. Making Newton-Type Methods Applicable to FL. 🗹 link

DEC-2022 EMNLP 2022, Abu Dhabi, UAE : Presenter in KAUST AI Iniative Booth.

OCT-2022 CS Ph.D. Proposal Defense, KSA: Dissertation Title: Optimization Methods and Software for Federated Learning. Committee members: Eric Feron, Marco Canini, Peter Richtarik.

JULY-2022 Workshop at ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing, Italy:

MARINA: Faster non-convex distributed learning with compression.

MAR-2022 Rising Stars in Al Symposium KAUST, KSA:

FL\_PyTorch: Optimization Research Simulator for Federated Learning

DEC-2021 ACM DistributedML2021, Rome: FL\_PyTorch: Optimization Research Simulator for Federated Learning.

JULY-2021 Poster and spotlight for in ICML-2021, Virtual:

MARINA Faster Non-Convex Distributed Learning with Compression.

APR-2021 Poster at Communication Efficient Distributed Optimization at NSF-TRIPODS Workshop, Virtual:

MARINA: Faster Non-Convex Distributed Learning with Compression.

FEB-2020 OpenTalks.Al conference, Russia: Huawei technologies for Al developers.

JULY-2019 Educational center Sirius, Russia. Deep Learning Course with D.Kamzolov and A.V. Gasnikov.

DEC-2018 Moscow Institute of Physics and Technologies, Russia. Guest lectures about subtle things around CART, Gradient Bossting and Random Forest: Slides: Link. Presentions: Session-#1, Session-#2.

APR-2016 GTC 2016, USA: Presenter in Driveworks NVIDIA booth.

AUG-2012 ACM SIGGRAPH 2012, USA: Presenter in CentiLeo booth. And a visitor from Fitting Reality.

### JUDGE OF THE WORK OF OTHERS

MARCH 11, 2024

- 1. Service as a referee for peer-reviewed journals or conference proceedings for ICML 2022, AISTATS 2023, JMLR 2024.
- 2. Participates in annual review processes for estimating the work of my colleagues in HUAWEI, NVIDIA, and Yandex.

## SCIENTIFIC PAPERS

UNLOCKING FEDNL: SELF-CONTAINED COMPUTE-OPTIMIZED IMPLEMENTATION  In https://burlachenkok.github.io/Unlocking-FedNL-at-KAUST-Al-Simposium/  Under a peer-review process.	2024
ERROR FEEDBACK RELOADED: FROM QUADRATIC TO ARITHMETIC MEAN OF SMOOTHNESS CONSTANTS  https://openreview.net/forum?id=Ch7WqGcGmb https://arxiv.org/abs/2402.10774  Accepted to presentation and proceedings to Twelfth International Conference on Learning Representations, ICLR-2	2024
FEDERATED LEARNING IS BETTER WITH NON-HOMOMORPHIC ENCRYPTION  Thttps://dl.acm.org/doi/10.1145/3630048.3630182  Thttps://arxiv.org/abs/2312.02074  Accepted to presentation and proceedings to 4th ACM International Workshop on Distributed Machine Learning.	2023
Error Feedback Shines when Features are Rare  https://arxiv.org/abs/2305.15264	2023
FEDERATED LEARNING WITH REGULARIZED CLIENT PARTICIPATION  Thttps://icml.cc/virtual/2023/27049  Thttps://arxiv.org/abs/2302.03662  Accepted to Federated Learning and Analytics in Practice. Workshop at ICML 2023.	2023
Sharper Rates and Flexible Framework for Nonconvex SGD with Client and Data Sampling https://openreview.net/forum?id=zKgJ6TWAFE https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.02275  **Accepted to Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR).**	2022
FEDERATED OPTIMIZATION ALGORITHMS WITH RANDOM RESHUFFLING AND GRADIENT COMPRESSION  **Thttps://icml.cc/virtual/2023/27050** https://arxiv.org/abs/2206.07021  **Accepted to Federated Learning and Analytics in Practice. Workshop at ICML 2023.**	2022
FASTER RATES FOR COMPRESSED FEDERATED LEARNING WITH CLIENT-VARIANCE REDUCTION  thttps://arxiv.org/abs/2112.13097  Accepted to SIAM Journal on Mathematics of Data Science (SIMODS).	2021
FL_PyTorch: Optimization Research Simulator for Federated Learning  https://dl.acm.org/doi/abs/10.1145/3488659.3493775/  https://arxiv.org/abs/2202.03099  Accepted to presentation and proceedings to 2nd ACM International Workshop on Distributed Machine Learning.	2021
MARINA: FASTER NON-CONVEX DISTRIBUTED LEARNING WITH COMPRESSION  If https://proceedings.mlr.press/v139/gorbunov21a.html  If https://arxiv.org/abs/2102.07845  Accepted to presentation and proceedings to Thirty-eighth International Conference on Machine Learning, ICML 202	2021 21.
Personalized federated learning with communication compression  the https://openreview.net/pdf?id=dZugyhbNFY the https://arxiv.org/abs/2209.05148  Accepted to Transactions on Machine Learning Research (TMLR).	2021 – 2022

# **≡** Engineering Competencies

Programming Languages that I have used	C89/C99, C++20/11/03, C#, Cython, Java ,x86/AArch64, NDA ASM
Scripting Languages that I have used	Python, Bash, Perl, and Cython which is between scipting and compile languages.
DSL Languages that I have used	Gl SL, TVM, Google Protobuf, CUDA, OpenCL, Matlab, R, SQL
Frameworks	Qt, CUDA, WinApi, Posix, OpenGL, OpenCL, PyTorch, TensorFlow, CvxPy
Operating Systems	Windows, Linux based, Orbis, XBox, Android, NDA OS-es
Development Environments	QtCreator, Visual Studio, Eclipse, WinDbg, Android Studio, TexStudio, Nsight
General purpose development tools	SysInternals,AqTime,Cmake,GNU Toolchain,CppCheck,Valgrind,Git,QMake
Typing DSL Languages	Latex, HTML, XML, Markdown
Areas in which I worked	Federated Learning, Stochastic Distributed Math Optimization, Computer Vision, Statistical Learning, System Programming, HPC and GPU Programming, Math Optimization, Computer Graphics, Computational Physics, Distributed Systems
Sport achievements	The Candidate Master in chess by FIDE. (My FIDE profile). Second Place in the KAUST Chess Tournament in Oct, 2022.

## TECHNICAL NOTES

TECHNICAL NOTE: FROM C++1998 TO C++2020

2022

🖸 github.com/burlachenkok/CPP\_from\_1998\_to\_2020/blob/main/Cpp-Technical-Note.md 🛮 🗗 Short Information The technical note is dedicated for all primary C++ programming language standards: C++03/98/11/14/17/20. The note has been adopted to AMD Inc. internal education web portal. Also it has been highly assessed by: (i) Marco Foco, Head of the Delegation for Italy ISO C++ JTC1/SC22/WG21; (ii) Prof. David Keyes, Director of Extreme Compute Research Center at KAUST.

TECHNICAL NOTE: EXPLORING PYTHON3 LANGUAGE FROM A COMPUTING PERSPECTIVE

2023

🖸 github.com/burlachenkok/exploring-python3/blob/main/python3-note.md 🛮 🗗 Short Information

The note contains a language tutorial, a description of several libraries, and a description of several low-level profiling tools for Linux/Posix OS and Windows OS Family. It has been adopted to Introduction to Data Science workshop series at KAUST.

### Selected Personal And Academic Projects

#### MATH OPTIMIZATION RESEARCH STUDIO

2020

🗹 Project report - Math Optimizaiton Research Studio 🖸 Description 🖸 Bitbucket repo

CS380: Math Optimization Research Studio. Self-developed command line interpreter with custom script language with self-developed backend computation in C++/CUDA.

C++ Linux Windows CUDA CMake Dot Google Test Python Bash

#### EXPERIMENTAL NEURAL NET FRAMEWORK

2019

☑ Report.CS230 - 2019 ☑ Poster CS230 - 2019 ☑ bitbucket repo ☑ Presentation

CS230': Experimental Neural Net Framework. Mentor: Steven Z. Chen(stevenzc@stanford.edu)

C++ Linux Windows CUDA Python CMake

### CONVEX OPTIMIZATION SOLVERS WITH LEVERAGING INTO GPU/CPU POWER FOR AI/ML

2018

Poster CS221 - 2018 Bitbucket repo

CS221: Convex optimization solvers with leveraging into GPU/CPU power for AI/ML. Mentor: Steven Diamond

C++ Linux Windows CUDA Python CMake Convex Optimization

#### CONVEX OPTIMIZATION FOR MACHINE LEARNING

2017

Poster CS229 - 2017. Presentation

Stanford, CS229: Convex Optimization for Machine Learning

C++ Visual Studio Numerical Linear Algebra Convex Optimization Python CMake

#### PLOTTER++. STANDALONE TOOL FOR PLOT IMAGES, GRAPHS, POINT CLOUDS, TEXT LOGS VIA OBTAINING DATA FROM TCP/IP 2017

An advanced scientific plotter tool suitable to use in connection with embedded systems.

C++ Linux Windows Embedded Systems Qt Python

### LANE DETECTION USING FOURIER BASED LINE DETECTOR

2016

Report Presentation

Lane detection using Fourier based line detector

### HTML REPORT GENERATOR FOR GOOGLE TESTS

2016

GitHub

Project goal is to generate and compare different Google Test reports from several launches. Project is used by Hyundai AutoEver, and Hapsoft Consulting.

Python HTML XML

## **66** REFERENCES

### **Andrew Ng**

### **Timour Paltashev**

Assistant Professor, Stanford, Letter AMD and Core faculty, Northwestern Polytechnic University, Letter

ang@cs.stanford.edu

@ Timour.Paltashev@amd.com

+1 (650)725-2593

+1 (408) 306 8508

### **Brad Osgood**

#### Jerome H. Friedman

Professor, Stanford, Under Request Professor, Stanford, Under Request

osgood@stanford.edu

@ jhf@stat.stanford.edu +1 (650) 723-9329

+1 (650) 387-1287